Never forget why you are the church.
Great.
Turn your Bibles to Romans chapter 9.
Romans chapter 9.
We are looking at the biblical truth of God's mercy here in this chapter.
Now, so far, we have seen the people
of mercy.
Paul is explaining to the Jews very
strategically how and why many of
them are hardened to the truth.
In other words, if God elected Israel,
chose Israel as his covenant people, how
in the world, could most Israelites have
rejected Christ?
Now you say, how do we know that Israel,
or at least most of the Israelites rejected Christ, will us think about it for a second?
They didn't just reject Jesus.
They hated him to the point of crucifying him.
They refused to believe Jesus so
much that they murdered him.
Now you say, well, it wasn't the Jews that murdered Christ,
it was the Romans, well, upon whose request?
The Jews, y'all women this morning.
It's going to be a long, long morning if you're not with me, okay?
So right here, Paul is clarifying the
problem to the Jews.
Those people of mercy are not who they thought they
were because the plan of mercy was not what they thought it was.
God chose Abraham.
Amen.
He chose Isaac, he chose Jacob.
That is, he chose Israel over Edom, all of this
according to his plan and will.
In the same theme of explaining God's plan of mercy, Paul now
brings up another set of questions that he knows the
Israelites would have asked, and that brings us to our text today.
If you look at Romans chapter 9, verse 19,
it says this, thou wilt say then unto me, why
does he find fault?
For who has resisted His will?
The title is unexplainable mercy.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you for your word.
God, I thank you, Lord, that even though some things are hard to understand,
as Peter says, God, I pray that you clarify
things to us today, Lord.
I don't have all the answers, but God, I thank you that we can put
our faith in you and trust you no matter what.
So, Lord God, I pray that you give me power, clarity, and liberty to preach this message.
Those have ears to hear, may they hear God.
We thank you, we love you, in Jesus' name.
Everybody said, amen.
This brings us.
We seen the people of mercy.
We've seen the plan of mercy.
Now we're going to see number three, the paradox of mercy.
We have to understand the tone of
this objection that Paul is bringing.
If God's purpose and plan is satisfied by
not electing some, how can the
unelected be blamed for their non-elect status
and be held in judgment?
And then they say, I mean, we know that we
cannot resist the will of God.
Now this sounds like it makes sense.
And honestly, in our human framework, it very much so does.
If God made it impossible for some to be saved, how
is he able to hold responsible that person?
And so Paul so clearly phases, why does
he still find fault?
This is where we get to the question of irresistible
grace.
And I want to point out a few things about this.
We're going to talk about this for a second.
First off, we have to realize that whereas in the text previous
to verse 19, we are speaking on specifically
national election.
In other words, he's elected and chosen Israel over Edom.
That is 2 nations.
But now we are talking more specifically regarding
individual salvation.
Now, I believe that scripture tells us there is a national and
partial hardening of Israel because they rejected
God, but what about the individual?
For example, right now, Americans, we send missionaries to Israel.
Think about that for a second.
We send missionaries to the
chosen land, God's chosen people to share
the gospel of Jesus Christ.
And guess what happens?
There's something that gets saved.
You understand what I'm saying?
So in other words, yes, we see a national hardening.
But the individual can still give their life to Christ.
By the way, we see in our nation today, I believe
that we are moving closer and closer to a national hardening.
And I see that because we see so many spiritual things happening
or churchianity things happening.
We think, man, that's so cool.
And look at these big churches and look at all these celebrities
giving their life to Christ.
I mean, let me just tell you something.
If it's not the real thing, it can hinder the real thing.
In other words, if we continue to move like we're
moving and make it okay to, when I get an award, say
that I love Jesus, but live like the devil in the world all
the other times and everyone knows it.
Listen, all that's gonna do is preach a false gospel.
God does not save you to keep you where you are at.
God saves you and delivers you from your sin.
He gives you a new life.
He makes you a new creation.
That's salvation.
That's the gospel of Jesus Christ.
So, we see here there's a national hardening.
Are y'all with me?
But there's also individual responsibility of salvation.
Now, we see here, the rich young.
There's 2 examples of scripture where it seems like God's
grace, that is, you know, the will of
God clearly being rejected.
And I want you to know something.
Listen, there's a lot of people that disagree.
I've read a lot of articles that say one thing about this
and say another thing about this.
So let's look at it together.
Amen?
Remember, some things are just hard to understand.
But I believe the 1st example of someone rejecting
the grace of God.
is in Mark chapter 10.
You can turn there or it's on the screen, but in Mark chapter
10, we're introduced to a rich young ruler.
And so in verse 17,
And when he was gone forth into the way, there came one running and kneeled to him and asked
him, good master, what shall I do that I may
inherit eternal life?
Now, I want to make a point here for a second.
The fact that he said good master, scholars
say that that kind of eliminates the possibility of him being a Roman.
So in other words, this good, this young rich ruler, which
he's in all, he's in other 2 gospels,
so they kind of name him there, but what
this is saying is that because he titles Christ
the way he does, he had to be a Jew.
So in other words, he knew the prophecy,
he knew the oracles of God.
He had studied the Old Testament.
So he says, what must I do to inherit eternal life?
That is a clear request of salvation here.
Would you agree?
He's saying, how can I be in 2025 terms,
how can I be saved?
Amen.
So Mark 10, 18, and Jesus said unto him, why cost thou me good?
There is none good but one, that is God.
There's a few things here.
I believe that Jesus really is stating his deity, right?
There's only one good, then that's God.
Jesus was God.
So in other words, what comes next supersedes
the goodness of how man sees goodness and
it shows what God sees is good because God is good.
So we see in verses 19 and 20.
Thou knowest the commandments.
Do not commit adultery.
Do not kill.
Do not steal, do not bear false witness, defraud not, honor
thy father and mother.
And man, this guy got excited.
He answered and said unto him, master, all these have I observed from
my youth, another proving statement that he couldn't
have been a Roman because Romans were pretty much pagans.
So he's saying, man, ever since I was a young person, man, I've
kept the law.
So he's excited.
He's like, man, I'm going to heaven.
Well, Jesus is now speaking in terms of what was custom of
the religion of that time.
Just do these things and all these little laws
that man has added.
And yes, we had the 10 commandments.
Yes, we have all the Levitical laws.
Yes, we have all these things, but we also want to put more burdens.
So the religious environment of
that time was extremely work-based.
And so Jesus exposing that.
In verse 21, the Jesus beholding him loved him.
If you ever read this in your Bible, your own personal Bible.
You need to circle that word loved.
Let's just think about this.
Then Jesus beholding him loved him.
That term for love is an intimate, deep love.
And said unto him, one thing thou lackest.
Go thy way, sell whatsoever, thou hast.
Give to the poor, and thou shalt have treasure in heaven and come.
Take up the cross, and follow me.
Jesus moves really from old on you from religious bondage to eternal freedom.
He introduces grace through faith here.
Follow me.
Jesus was not going after this man's church attendance role or Bible
app streak, but rather his heart.
See, Jesus had to have known, yeah, this dude's a pretty good dude.
In the world's eyes, right?
And everyone is watching him and he's successful, he's good.
He's obeyed the law, but his heart was in
love with his possessions more than he loved Jesus.
And so let's think about this for a second.
I'm not preaching this as a whole message.
I'm just trying to state a fact here.
He goes and says, what must I do to inherit eternal life?
Jesus tells him, follow me.
Turn your heart posture towards me.
Jesus is not saying, if you do this, you'll be
saved, like go and do an action.
He says, listen, reveal your heart posture, get
rid of your idols and follow me.
You've gotta love me more than anything else.
Jesus is loving him saying this.
What happens here?
Verse 22, and he was sad at that saying.
And went away grieved.
Why?
For he had great possessions.
If God was not drawing him.
Why go away grieved?
Obviously, he knew that he just made a decision.
Because Jesus literally says, hey, get rid of this stuff.
Follow me.
And what did he do?
He left because he had so much stuff.
By the way, today, don't do that today.
There's nothing worth rejecting Christ.
The word greed means to distress grieve.
It used it's used to denote feelings of sadness or remorse.
This young ruler makes it evident that when given a decision between Jesus
and his many worldly possessions, he chose his possessions,
therefore forfeiting eternal life because he would not make Jesus Lord.
He rejected grace standing right in front of him.
This was this was not a hardening.
God the Bible literally says, and Jesus loved him and told him, follow me.
This was not a hardening.
This was a decision.
The next example may not be as obvious, but still reveals this troubling truth.
So bear with me here.
When Paul was arrested and appealed to Caesar.
The governor at the time, Festus had spoke with Herod Agrippa
regarding his case, and Festus admittedly said, I
can't really find fault in this dude.
And so intrigued, the gripper said, well, I want to hear him for myself.
So they kind of made it a big thing and had a big audience and
all the all the, you know, pomp and circumstance, all the stuff, you know, and and
then so Paul then sees an opportunity and
he speaks boldly.
Acts 26, one and 3 says this.
Then Agrippa said in the Paul, thou art permitted to speak for thyself.
Then Paul stretched forth the hand and answered for himself.
I think myself happy, King Agrippa, because I shall answer
for myself this day before thee, touching all the things whereof I
am accused of the Jews, especially because I know thee
to be an expert in all the customs and questions which are among the Jews.
Wherefore I beseech thee to hear me patiently.
So right here, Paul is setting up the situation.
It's almost like 2025 terms.
How you go to church anywhere?
None of y'all are evangelical work of evangelists at all.
You've never, you understand what I'm saying?
We don't just boldly say, hey, you know Jesus, we always have to say, you
go to church anywhere?
And then we hope they say yes, so we can move along, right?
Is that not what we do?
No, no.
So he's prepping the table here.
He's saying, listen, just listen to me patiently.
I know you understand what I'm about to say.
Paul then gives his testimony in Jesus Christ.
He tells of his encounter with Christ on the road to Damascus.
Acts 26, skipping all the way to 19 and 20.
Whereupon, O King Agrippa, I was not disobedient unto the heavenly vision.
But show it 1st unto them of Damascus and at Jerusalem,
and throughout all the coast of Judea, and then to the Gentiles,
that they should repent and turn to God and do works,
meet for repentance.
There's his plea for repentance.
Acts 26, 22, and 23.
having therefore obtained help of God.
I continue unto this day witnessing both the small
and great, saying none other things than those which the prophets
in Moses did say should come.
Remember what he told them, you understand these things, king.
That Christ should suffer.
And that he should be the 1st that should rise from the dead,
and should show a light unto the people, and to the Gentiles.
There's the reason why right there.
He's saying, listen, hey, we need to repent because Jesus
has risen.
He's alive.
Upon hearing this, we have 2 different responses.
You got Festus, right?
He was probably a kind of a, you know, dummy.
And he said in verse 24 and 25.
And as he thus spoke for himself, Fest said with a loud voice, Paul!
Thou art beside thyself.
Much learning has made thee mad.
2025 terms.
Dude, you're crazy.
Like, you're not making any sense, but he said, I am not mad.
This is Paul, most noble Festus, but speak forth the words of
truth and soberness.
He is proclaiming the good news.
Now here's where it gets interesting.
Y'all with me so far?
Okay, let me know a little bit of it now and again.
Okay?
Obviously, Paul realized that Fest is nowhere near the
heart posture to receive Christ.
Now, I'm just reading this.
listen, go home and read it for yourself here.
He's thinking, man, Festus, his response was, you're insane, you're crazy.
You've learned too much, you're mad.
So Paul sees that.
He reads the situation here.
So he turns his attention to King Agrippa.
Verses 26 and 32.
For the king knoweth these things.
Before whom also I speak freely, for I am persuaded that
none of these things are hidden from him.
But this thing was not done in a corner.
In other words, saying, hey, listen, Jesus was not a private savior.
There's nothing proud about Christ.
He proclaimed the truth boldly in the streets.
Everyone at this time heard about Christ.
They either loved them or you hated them.
So he's saying, king.
You're not out of this.
King Agrippa, believest thou the prophets?
I know that thou believe.
Then Agrippa said unto Paul, here's where it gets good.
Almost thou persuadest me to be a Christian.
Now.
Let's read the 1st 2 and I'm going to explain that phrase.
And Paul said, I would to God that not only thou, but also all that
hear me this day, we're both almost in all together, such as I am, except these bonds.
And when he had thus spoken, the king rose up and the governor and
Bernice, and they sat with them, and when they were gone aside,
they talked between themselves saying, this man has done nothing worthy
of death or bonds, then said Agrippa unto Festus, this
man might have been set at liberty if he had not appealed into Caesar.
King Agrippa knew what Paul was talking about.
He knew the customs and oracles of God that came from the prophets.
No doubt he knew the prophecies of the coming Messiah.
But his response was different than manifestus.
Some translations can word his response in such a way like
the KJV that can be a tad confusing if you think about it, right?
Then Agrippa said in the Paul, almost doubt persuades me to be a Christian.
Instantly you think, man, he, he, He's about to become a Christian.
But the actual phrasing of that should read more like this.
Do you think that in such a short time, you can persuade me to be made a Christian?
Some can look at this and think that his response is equivalent
to the outright ignorance of Festus.
But I'm not convinced of that.
Festus thought Paul was crazy.
Agrippa knew what Paul was not just saying, But
Agrippa knew what he was doing.
You're trying to lead me to Christ.
You're trying to make me a Christian.
There's a reason, uh, I don't know if you know or
not, but I enjoy going to the sauna, right?
and tell the gospel and stuff, okay?
Fully clothed, all the stuff.
But anyway.
So, But I'm telling you, I
have, I need to start jotting down the conversations that
I have because there's so many.
And I always, you know, was sitting there and it's easy to preach on Hell
in a Sonic because it is hot, guys.
I'm telling you, like, listen, if you think this is hot, let me tell you something.
Imagine that one at the door, you know what I'm saying?
Like a jail sale.
But anyway, so, um, but I had these conversations
and and, and, and I can tell when someone knows what I'm doing.
I love the ones that it kind of hits them out of nowhere.
They're like, oh, that's cool.
Well thank you for telling me that and or we have a conversation more
about Christ and they start opening up a little bit and I'm able to Minnesota them.
But there are others.
That the moment, the moment.
I say, hey, you know, did you grow up here?
Because let me just tell you something, there's a lot of people moving here.
Do y'all know that?
There's a whole new mission field out here in Lebanon, Tennessee.
Let me just tell you.
Okay?
And there's an old one too, but there's a new one as well.
All right?
Hey, you know, you grow up in Lebanon?
Yeah, no, whatever they say.
I said, that's cool.
I said, well, man, how long have you lived here?
And they'll tell me.
And I'll go, okay, well, have you found a home church yet?
Well, I never opened.
I never opened.
I never open with, my name's Pastor
Jacob, I'm Cedar Girl Baptist Church.
If you're not a pastor, you don't understand.
Don't tell people I'm the past at the moment.
I meet them.
That shuts down the conversation sometimes.
And some of y'all do it in spite.
I know y'all do.
Hey, this is my pastor.
No, let me just be a person for a second.
So anyway, so I'm like, you know, you go to church anywhere, and they're
like, ah, you know, yeah, I don't really, you know, not really my thing.
I said, oh, okay.
I said, I get that, you know.
I said, well, and I'll ask, why is it not your thing?
I'm like, ah, you know.
And then I'll say, well, do you know Jesus?
And instantly, there's there's certain ones, instantly, like, I got my own thing.
We're good.
And what they're trying to say is, I know what you're doing.
And I'm like, I don't care.
You're saying?
And so what I'm trying to say is very similar to that.
I'm convinced that Agrippa knew exactly what Paul was doing.
Man, you're trying to make me a Christian.
You think in this little time, in just that little testimony that you give.
that I'm going to receive Christ.
Now, how does this connect to Romans nine?
Well, let's look back at the objection
Paul brings up in verse 19.
That will say unto me then, why does
he yet find fault for who has resisted his will?
Our culture today would ask the same question.
If God decides everything, the why, then why should I be blamed?
We like to, we live in a society and a culture that deflex blame.
We don't like the concept of giving our life to Christ because we have to admit that we're a sinner.
We have to admit that the way we're living is wrong.
We have to admit that we are living far from God,
living in pride, living as sons of disobedience.
We had to admit these things.
We had to realize that we need a savior.
But how, listen, if God decides that
God, how in the world can we be blamed?
Two questions.
And with 2 words?
The answer be summed up in 2 words.
Y'all ready for these 2 words?
Your sin.
My sin.
We are ultimately responsible for judgment.
The only way out of this is to be perfect.
That is sinless.
And because we are not and cannot be that.
Jesus, who was perfect and sinless, had to pay our
sin debt with his own blood.
It is through him, and only through him can
we obtain mercy.
That is eternal life.
Why don't like that plan?
I don't like that plan.
Well, Paul has some words for you as well.
Look at verse 2021.
Nay, but 0 man, who art thou?
that repliest against God.
Shall the thing form, say to him that formed it?
Why hast thou made me thus?
Had not the potter power over the clay of the same lump
to make one vessel and honor and another unto dishonor?
It's almost like your kid questioning what you're doing.
Well, I don't know if this is still politically correct.
I'm sure it's not.
But I used to get told, I brought you into this world.
And I'll bring you out.
No one ever said that?
Okay, what does that mean?
I mean, is that cute you?
Why, why?
Because when a kid, and you're like thinking, hold on now, you can't,
why question me, you don't know, you don't know enough to question me.
You don't understand things to question me.
I use the thing all the time.
Why do kids say, why do I got to brush my teeth?
Because your teeth are right out your head.
But you don't fully understand that.
So just go brush your teeth.
You see what I'm saying?
How could the potter be questioned by the clay?
Paul here is quoting a familiar analogy depicting the creator and the created.
God obviously is the potter.
We are the clay.
It is nonsensical to think that clay can question the pot of
the clay is at the mercy of the potter's hands and plan for it.
Out of the same lump.
There are some made for honorable, noble use, and others dishonorable, that means common use.
But here's the detail many want to ignore.
They say, oh, there it is.
Both come from the same lump of clay.
In other words, we are all condemned already.
A useless lump of clay, our sin has separated us from God.
Ephesians 2 tells us what we all are aside from Christ
in verses one and 3, and you hath equickened, who
were dead in trespasses and sins, wherein in time past you
walked according to the course of this world.
According to the prince of the power of the air, the spirit that now worketh
in the children of disobedience, among whom also we all had our conversation
in times past, in the lust of our flesh,
fulfilling the desires of the flesh and of the mind, and we're by nature
the children of wrath, even as others.
I challenge you to think about who you were before you knew Christ.
That is who you are.
And if you are honest with yourself, you'll say, amen, so be it.
But then there's 2 beautiful words in verse four.
But God.
But God?
These 2 words are what introduces his plan of mercy,
but God, who is rich in mercy.
For his great love, wherewith he loved us, even when we were dead in
sins hath quickened us together with Christ by grace.
Are you saved?
And hath raised us up together, and made us sit together in heavenly
places in Christ Jesus, that in the ages to come, he might show the exceeding
riches of his grace and his kindness towards us through Christ, Jesus.
Is there a name that provides continuity in those verses?
Christ Jesus?
That's the common denominator.
Remember those 2 words that hold us responsible for the coming judgment, your sin?
My sin.
God provides a way of salvation through 2 greater words, but God.
Now, I pray y'all didn't miss that, but nothing is greater than the love and mercy of God.
Never forget it or take that.
For granted.
So Paul sharply corrects the notion of deflecting
responsibility because of God's election and sovereignty.
Just because we cannot fully understand something, hear me?
doesn't give us the right to reject or change biblical
truth in order to make it more compatible for us.
And what I truly believe is this.
Okay?
In our, and you need to know these things.
In our church society, church culture today, what
we've done is we have tried and made things more compatible
for us in our minds.
And so in a chapter like 8 and 9 of
Romans, what we do is say, okay, well, you're either on this side or you're on that side.
In other words, you are either a Calvinist or you are an Armenian.
If you haven't heard those words, go look them up and study them.
Don't study them too hard, I'm just kidding.
study them.
But seriously, listen, you got some beliefs of the Armenians
and nose beliefs.
The big ones are contradictory to the Calvinists.
They look at the same text and see different things.
And so what they do is they go up against each other.
If you're not an Armenian, you must be that.
If you're not that, you must be that.
And it's more compatible that way.
Let me just tell you something.
I want you to understand.
Our human minds cannot fully comprehend
how is God all sovereign?
But yet how do we have free will?
I'm just going to be honest with you.
I sit in my office all the time.
Read my Bible.
Not being arrogant but probably more than you do.
And sit there over and over again thinking, God, I just want
a nice little answer for this.
Because I do believe that you know everything, because if
I didn't, that would be, you know, heretical, that
would be changing the character of God to make it make sense for me.
But I also know that whosoever shall call upon the name of Lord, shall be saved.
So make it make sense.
And I believe he did, but you just don't want to accept it.
We like systems more than we like, just God's truth sometimes.
And she said, how do, how do, how do we?
I believe God gave us this phrase grace through faith.
There's the bridge.
Why do we have the question?
You say, what if I'm a vessel of wrath?
I'm getting ahead of myself here, but I just gotta say, what am I, a vessel of wrath?
Listen, hey, get saved.
Put your faith in God.
Are y'all with me this morning?
But we have a society that says, well, I'm going
to change this biblical truth in order to make it more compatible.
I want to kind of humble you for a 2nd just like
God's word humbled me this week.
If you disagree with what God says about something,
You hear me?
If that's you, you're wrong.
Young women is mine.
You ain't right.
If you look at something and say, well, yeah, that's cool, but you
need to change your perspective on what you're thinking about.
People all the time say, well, you know, I mean, back in the day, homosexuality was wrong.
No, no, no, no, no.
God said it's wrong yesterday, today, and tomorrow.
Well, you know, God cares about life, but just not
this, you know, A, B, C, that kind of life.
No, no, no, no.
God is the giver of life.
God literally sent his son Jesus so that we could live.
You see what I'm saying?
So, oh, well, you know, I just, you know, I just feel like I can have church in
the woods, you know what I'm saying?
And I know what the scripture says, but that's
just kind of said, no, it's not.
Get your behind in church.
Assemble together.
Do not forsake the assembling.
Why?
Because we need this.
You know why I say that I want every man to go to that training?
Because some of y'all, I know what you're thinking right now.
I don't need no training.
Then why aren't you living as victorious as you could be?
As a man, think about it for a second.
Why are you struggling so much?
You may not come up here and tell me all your struggles?
But why are we as men struggling so much?
Why are we as men letting women do the things in leading that we should be doing?
Oh, but I don't need no training.
You need to change your perspective.
If you disagree with God, God's not wrong.
Did I say that already?
You're wrong.
I'm wrong.
Listen, there's times, I'm just gonna be honest with you, there's times where I've read a scripture.
And I thought, there's no way that can be.
And so I'll read it again and read it again.
And look at all the commentaries.
And what I find out is this.
I'm sitting here, I don't want to receive this truth because the
truth kind of hurts my feelings a little bit, but you know what, God?
I'm gonna have to humble myself because it's what it says.
Don't ever think God's gonna adapt to you.
Who are you?
Who am I?
We need to believe God when he gives us truth.
So what does he say about scripture then?
Well, Hebrews 4.12.
For the word of God is quick and powerful and sharper than any 2 edged sword?
Piercing even to the dividing asunder of soul and spirit,
and of the joints and marrow, and as a discerner, the thoughts and intents of the heart.
If God's word does not hurt your feelings throughout the week, you're not reading it.
You know, people like to go to these churches where they, they, they,
they like to kind of tiptoe around scripture.
Well, I've got a group of people in my church that wouldn't like that.
Well, they need to hear it the most then.
Amen?
Ever seen a 2 edged sword?
Okay, Joe?
You're my guy today.
Imagine I had a 2 edged sword.
Stringing.
It's in it's in Joe right now.
Okay?
All right.
Joe, I just put a 2 edged sword in your sternum.
That's how you're gonna react?
Okay, thank you.
It hurt.
I miss dude's tough as nails, man.
He's like, huh.
Think about it.
But if I physically just can't, we, it would hurt.
There would be a reaction to the hurt.
But see, here's the thing.
What we want to do is we want to take that 2 edged sword and we want to toss it aside
and we want to start giving high fives out.
Hey man, you keeping your sin, dude.
You keep on doing, God loves you no matter what.
God loves you enough to tell you what you need.
And that's Jesus.
And you need deliverance from your sin.
You need forgiveness.
You need to repent.
It's a 2 edged sword.
The only comfort we need to enjoy is when God's word does hurt so we
can trust it to steer us directly.
2nd Timothy 3, 16 and 70.
All scripture is given by inspiration to God, and it's profitable for doctrine,
for reproof, for correction, for instruction and righteousness, that
the man of God may be perfect thoroughly furnished unto all good works.
When is the last time you were corrected from doing wrong and enjoyed it?
Huh?
Anyone ever driven with their spouse?
Do you get corrected in the car?
Hey, that's not the speed limit.
Chill.
Stop talking.
Hey, uh, oh, this one gets me, okay?
It's green.
Right?
You just ran a red light.
Think about it.
Man, I don't like getting corrected.
You know what I'm saying?
Like, we get right sometimes, and we get right sometimes.
Man, man, well, Tom, hey, we ain't got to do some things a little differently.
You know what I'm saying?
you know, and then I'll say, okay, because, you know, I counsel.
So, unfortunately, Heather has to deal with that a lot, so I'll be like,
hey, you know, you say something, then I respond to that something.
And then you can respond to my response, and then we'll get better.
right here, right now.
And some, that doesn't work as often as you think it would.
But I will say, hey, do this, do that, do this, do that.
And so we'll get right and stuff and we'll do good for a little bit.
You know, I help around here, help you, you know what I'm saying?
And then all of a sudden I won't do what I said I do.
You know what she does?
She lets me know.
You ever been letting know?
Hey, I remember that conversation we had?
Yeah, your clothes are still right there.
Wow, I don't understand.
We had a conversation about this.
And you said you would do this.
She corrects me.
She rebukes me.
She hurts my feelings.
But listen, as silly and funny as that is, we
have to understand, God's word is not permitted
to be used to guide us in sin,
but rather to guide us in this life for Jesus.
So because we battle with the flesh, there's going to be a conflict there.
There's gonna be some tension.
There's going to be some hurt.
Y'all with me, amen?
But we can appreciate it, but it still hurts.
We must focus on why.
Why are we being corrected?
So that we may become fully mature into faith, adequate for
his use, and equip for good works.
So in response to questioning God's plan of mercy, Romans 9,
verse 20, again, nay, but, oh man, who art thou that repliest against God?
In other words, who are you to question God?
He then speaks to God's unquestionable ability and right.
Romans 9, 22, 23.
What if God, willing to show his wrath and the maker's power known, endured
with much long suffering, the vessels of wrath fitted to destruction?
And that he might make known the riches of glory on the vessels of mercy,
which he had afore before afore prepared unto glory.
He expounds on his concept of objects of mercy and objects of wrath.
Look again at verse 9, verse 22.
What if God will want to show his wrath and to make his power known,
endure with much long suffering, the vessels of wrath fitted to destruction?
God's will is to show wrath against sin.
That's going to happen.
I want you to understand something.
Sinners who refuse to put their faith in Jesus Christ will
endure this wrath for eternity in hell.
Are y'all with me?
Without getting into the weeds here, scripture teaches us that
hell is an eternal conscience torment.
We do not I do not believe in annihilation.
There is a hell created for
those who reject Christ.
However, we see that God is long suffering even
towards these vessels of wrath.
How can this be?
Remember, Jesus came for all, died for all, rose again for all.
Would you consider God being patient even with rejecting sinners a good thing?
Would that be good for his character?
Would that show how good he is?
Of course it is.
Why do you show patience towards your wayward child?
Listen, think about it for a 2nd.
some of y'all know exactly what I'm talking about.
You show patience at the patient.
If everyone's telling you, give up on them.
Just stop.
Forget about them.
And what do you do?
You keep on praying.
You keep on trying.
You keep on pursuing.
Why?
Because you love them.
They're wayward.
They're making their own decision.
Man, they're fitted for destruction.
Patience is not equated with tolerance here.
Why does this matter?
Well, again, Romans 2.4.
Or to spy the style, the riches of his goodness and forbearance and long suffering?
Not knowing that the goodness of God leadeth thee to repentance?
God is not displaying a passive, long suffering and endurance.
He is not simply neglecting to pour out his wrath.
That day is coming.
Rather, he is actively enduring in order
to show his goodness, even to those who are rejecting him.
What a good God we serve.
Now let's move on to Romans 923.
and that he might make known the riches of his glory on the
vessels of mercy, which he had afore prepared unto glory.
How does God prepare?
That is prepared in advance the vessels of mercy.
Through grace, through Jesus, he has prepared us and is preparing
us for glory.
Ephesians 316 that he would grant you according to the riches of
his glory, to be strengthened with might by his spirit in the inner man.
Church, it is long suffering.
He is long suffering to the lost and preparing the saved.
And if the lost stay lost, they're adequately fitted for wrath due to their sin.
And the ones that are saved, they're adequately fitted for glory because
they put their faith in God.
Now, that's not a paradox enough for you.
Here's where he really confounds the Israelite audience.
We're almost done here.
Someone say, well, almost done.
Okay, don't get too excited.
Yes, disrespectful.
Romans 9.24 says this, even us whom he hath called, not of
the Jews only, but also the Gentiles.
This is the main point.
Do you see the beauty in this?
God has hardened the already rebellious hearts of many of the Jews.
For the purpose of bringing the gospel to the Gentiles, therefore, fulfilling
the promise he made to Abraham all the way back in Genesis 22, 18.
And in thy seed shall all the nations of the earth be blessed because
thou hast obeyed my voice.
You say, when did this happen?
When was the shift?
Well, we see that in Acts 13, 44, and 49, and the next Sabbath
day came almost the whole city together to hear the word of God.
Wouldn't that be awesome this morning almost the whole city?
I love how it says almost the whole city.
That's probably how humans are.
But think about it.
Everyone came to hear the word of God.
They didn't come for the cafe.
They didn't come for this.
I'm not saying that's all bad, but they came to hear the word of God.
By the way, if you're here for anything but the word of God, then you're probably here for the wrong reason.
So they came for the word of God.
To hear the word, God.
But when the Jews saw the multitudes, they were filled with the envy and
spake against those which were spoken by Paul, contradicting and blaspheming.
In other words, they're sabotaging this church service.
They're saying, hey, listen, I know that he said this, but it's really what he meant.
They start sowing seeds of vision and blaspheming and contradicting everything Paul was saying.
Then Paul and Barnamus waxed bold and said it
was necessary that the word of God should 1st have been spoken to you, talking
about the Israelites, the Jews.
But seeing he put it from you.
Seeing that you're rejecting it and judge yourselves unworthy of
everlasting life, lo, we turn to the Gentiles.
For so hath the Lord, God commanded us, saying, I have set thee
to be a light of the Gentiles, that thou shouldest be for salvation unto the ends of the earth.
And when the Gentiles heard this, they were glad.
and glorified the word of the Lord.
And as many as were ordained, the eternal life believed,
and the word of the Lord was published throughout all the region.
Romans 116, for I'm not ashamed of the gospel of Christ, but is the power
of God and the salvation, everyone that believeth.
to the Jew 1st and also to the Greek.
Guys, I understand.
You might read this, and you could potentially have more questions than what I've answered.
And to that I say, listen, hey, we serve
a deep, mighty great God.
His ways are simply higher than ours.
I know that in that verse right there, as we read it,
If you go back to, uh, uh, the
one in Acts 13, it says, as many as were ordained to eternal life believed.
You say, oh, well, you have to, you know, that's
talking about the election and all that.
Yes, it is.
However, But it's a power gun and salvation.
Everyone that believeth the Jew 1st and also the Greek, whosoever shall
call upon the name of the Lord shall be saved is grace through faith.
that we were saved.
I can't answer all the questions on this, but I think that his plan of mercy included me.
Because if it didn't, I'd be condemned already.
So what about you?
Let me ask you this.
What kind of vessel are you?
What is God preparing you for?
Wrath or glory.
Preacher, how do I know what kind of vessel I'm
how do I know if I'm being prepared for for
glory or for wrath?
How do I know?
Well, you put your faith in Jesus.
The Bible literally says in 1st John, it says, I write you these things so
that you may know that you have eternal life.
What does it say?
He that has a son, has life.
He that has not the son has not life.
So it has bad eyes closed all this place.
Let me ask you, do you have the son?